<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Rationality Freiburg</title><link>http://www.rationality-freiburg.de/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Rationality Freiburg</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 13:52:32 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.rationality-freiburg.de/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Rationality Freiburg Welcome Meetup (May 13th)</title><link>http://www.rationality-freiburg.de/posts/meetup-2022-05-13/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 13:52:32 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://www.rationality-freiburg.de/posts/meetup-2022-05-13/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Deutsche Version weiter unten.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="freiburg-rationality-welcome-2022-05-13.ics">Download iCal (.ics) event&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/rationality-freiburg/events/285436952/">Find event on meetup.com&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/events/YyqngHiRrzFKrxfMK/rationality-freiburg-welcome-meetup">Find event on LessWrong&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="english">English&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Rationality Freiburg is a meeting place for LessWrong or SCC readers as well as other people interested in Rationality. Rationality is the desire to see the world as it is, in particular using empirical sciences as well as the development of tools for reaching personal goals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This meetup is intended to invite newcomers and anyone who is curious to see what this is all about. Come, have a look and you may be surprised!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is no fixed agenda or structure other than talking and getting to know each other. If there is enough interest we will give an introduction to Bayesian thinking and how to apply it in your day-to-day life.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We will meet at 17:00 pm CEST (German time) at the Schwabentor in Freiburg and will walk up the Schloßberg to the Kanonenplatz and then decide where to go next. We will carry a sign saying &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.rationality-freiburg.de">www.rationality-freiburg.de&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;, so you can easily find us.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/way/129932309">https://www.openstreetmap.org/way/129932309&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Feel free to just turn up, but if you want to reach out or RSVP that would be even better &lt;a href="mailto:info@rationality-freiburg.de">info@rationality-freiburg.de&lt;/a> .&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We will decide on using German or English as the main language depending on the people who turn up. Just come, we will figure it out!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.rationality-freiburg.de">www.rationality-freiburg.de&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="schwabentor.jpg" alt="Schwabentor, Freiburg" title="Schwabentor, Freiburg">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Schwabentor, Freiburg (&lt;a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwabentor_(Freiburg_im_Breisgau)#/media/Datei:Schwabentor_Freiburg.JPG">source&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="deutsch">Deutsch&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Rationality Freiburg ist ein Treffpunkt für LessWrong- oder SCC-Leser sowie für andere an Rationalität (Rationality) interessierte Menschen. Rationality ist der Wunsch, die Welt so zu sehen, wie sie ist, insbesondere mit Hilfe der empirischen Wissenschaften sowie der Entwicklung von Werkzeugen zur Erreichung persönlicher Ziele.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dieses Treffen soll Neulinge und alle Neugierigen einladen, die wissen wollen, worum es hier geht. Kommt einfach, schaut euch um und lasst euch überraschen!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Es gibt keine feste Tagesordnung, sondern die Möglichkeit, miteinander zu reden und sich kennen zu lernen. Wenn genügend Interesse besteht, werden wir eine Einführung in das Bayes&amp;rsquo;sche Denken geben und zeigen, wie man es im täglichen Leben anwenden kann.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wir treffen uns um 17:00 Uhr MESZ am Schwabentor in Freiburg und werden den Schloßberg hinauf zum Kanonenplatz gehen und dann entscheiden, wohin wir weitergehen. Wir werden ein Schild dabeihaben auf dem &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.rationality-freiburg.de">www.rationality-freiburg.de&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; steht, damit ihr uns problemlos findet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/way/129932309">https://www.openstreetmap.org/way/129932309&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ihr könnt einfach kommen, aber wenn ihr euch anmelden wollt, wäre das noch besser &lt;a href="mailto:info@rationality-freiburg.de">info@rationality-freiburg.de&lt;/a> .&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wir werden uns für Deutsch oder Englisch als Hauptsprache entscheiden, je nachdem, welche Leute kommen. Kommt einfach, das klappt!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.rationality-freiburg.de">www.rationality-freiburg.de&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>What Is Rationality (Not)?</title><link>http://www.rationality-freiburg.de/posts/what-is-rationality/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 14:47:17 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://www.rationality-freiburg.de/posts/what-is-rationality/</guid><description>&lt;p>Rationality is a desire to see the world as it &lt;strong>is&lt;/strong>, not as you wished it to be. It is about accepting the fallibility of human cognition and nevertheless striving to reach valuable conclusions. It&amp;rsquo;s applying empirical thinking to prove yourself wrong. It&amp;rsquo;s being humble and thirsty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rationality is not about being cold, unfeeling and robotic. It is not prioritizing abstract logic over human emotion. Rather it is accepting human emotion, both in oneself and others and understanding its beauty and purpose. If you are baffled by &lt;em>irrational&lt;/em> behaviour it&amp;rsquo;s actually you who is behaving &lt;em>irrationally&lt;/em> by expecting anything else.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rationality is not supressing that warm glow you feel when hearing a beautiful piece of music. Rather it is bathing in that feeling. And maybe afterwards, if you are so inclined, reflecting in amazement how it is possible to produce such an effect.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="further-reading">Further reading&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Julia Galef&amp;rsquo;s talk &amp;ldquo;The Straw Vulcan&amp;rdquo; debunks some common myths.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Fv1nMc-k0N4" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Julia explains why epistemically it&amp;rsquo;s bad form to ask something like:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I can&amp;rsquo;t understand how people could think science detracts from the beauty of the physical world.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/chALQCm9VgE" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Welcome!</title><link>http://www.rationality-freiburg.de/posts/welcome/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 14:25:43 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://www.rationality-freiburg.de/posts/welcome/</guid><description>&lt;p>Welcome to &lt;a href="https://www.rationality-freiburg.de">rationality-freiburg.de&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Read &lt;a href="http://www.rationality-freiburg.de/about/" title="About">About&lt;/a> to learn more.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>